Guide to Indian Ledger Drawings by Koba and Etahdleuh Doanmoe.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Indian ledger drawings by Koba and Etahdleuh Doanmoe.
1878-1889
1878-1885
WA MSS S-2942
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.1
(1 volume)
Ledger with drawings, sketches, and watercolors by Kiowa Indians Koba and Etahdleuh Doanmoe, circa 1878-1885, while they were students at the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, or imprisoned at Fort Marion in Saint Augustine, Florida. The ledger includes twenty-three pages of artwork attributed to Koba, four pages attributed to Doanmoe, and two pages of unattributed work.
1 v. (29 p. ): ill.; 32 cm.
Koba, 1848-1880
Doanmoe, Etahdleuh, 1856-1888
General note
Title devised by cataloger.
General note
The front flyleaf has an ownership inscription of Francis "Frank" Murray Wynkoop, as well as a label for the Villagra Book Shop of Santa Fe, New Mexico.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Formerly owned by Francis "Frank" Murray Wynkoop. Formerly owned by the Villagra Book Shop. Santa Fe, New Mexico. Purchased from William Reese Company (Heritage Auction Galleries' sale, 2009 September 19, lot 55145) on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Koba (1848-1880)
Koba (also known as Wild Horse) was a Kiowa. He was part of a Kiowa Indian band that surrendered during the Red River War on February 18, 1875, and accused of stealing horses and mules in Texas and participating in an August 1874 skirmish at the Wichita Agency.
In April 1875, United States authorities transferred him to Fort Marion in Saint Augustine, Florida. Following his release from Fort Marion in April 1878, Koba attended the Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute in Virginia. From June to October 1879, he assisted farmers in Lee, Massachusetts. Koba attended the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, from October 1879 to September 1880, and trained to become a tinsmith.
He died of tuberculosis during a visit to his home in Anadarko, Kiowa Agency.
Etahdleuh Doanmoe (1856-1888)
Etahdleuh Doanmoe (also known as Etahdleeuh, Etadeleuh, Hunting Boy, and Boy Hunting) was the son of a Kiowa father and Mexican mother. He was part of a Kiowa band led by Lone Wolf that surrendered during the Red River War on February 23., 1875, and accused of attacking buffalo hunters at Adobe Walls, Texas, in spring 1874.
In April 1875, United States authorities transferred him to Fort Marion in Saint Augustine, Florida. During his imprisonment, he also served as a quartermaster sergeant for prison commander Richard Henry Pratt (1840-1924).
Following his release from Fort Marion in April 1878, Doanmoe attended the Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute in Virginia. In 1879, he travelled to the Indian Territory to recruit pupils to attend the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania. He intermittently attended and worked at the school from 1879 to 1887. From February to May 1880, Doanmoe worked in the Bureau of Ethnology at the Smithsonian Institution.
In 1882, he married Laura Tone-adle-mah and they had a son, Richard Doanmoe (born 1886). He also trained as a Presbyterian missionary and returned to the reservation in January 1888. Later that year he died of tuberculosis in Anadarko, Kiowa Agency.
Scope and Contents
Ledger with drawings, sketches, and watercolors by Kiowas Koba and Etahdleuh Doanmoe, circa 1878-1885, while they were students at the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, or imprisoned at Fort Marion in Saint Augustine, Florida. The ledger includes twenty-three pages of artwork attributed to Koba, four pages attributed to Doanmoe, and two pages of unattributed work.
Images of Kiowa material culture include depictions of strike-a-lite bags, tipis, and war shields, as well as individual images of a cradleboard, an eagle-feather headdress, a lance, a parfleche, and a shirt. Other material objects include a cooking pot, a knife, and a rifle, as well as several wagons. The ledger also includes depictions of horses and buffalo, as well as a drawing of a stag elk.
Images of religious symbols include a Thunderbird and a horned mystical creature, as well as material related to the Native American Church, including buttons of peyote (Lophophora williamsii) and geometric designs used in ceremonies. One drawing depicts Rainy Mountain (Sépyáldá), an important cultural site for Kiowas.
The ledger includes a view of a train with an engineer operating a locomotive pulling railcars with American Indian passengers, as well as a view of a stockade fort flying a United States flag.
Portraits of American Indian women and men include a representation of a man with smallpox. A copy drawing reproduces a studio portrait photograph that depicts Kiowa Indian chief Stumbling Bear created in 1869 by photographer William S. Soule.
Before its use by Koba and Etahdleuh Doanmoe, the ledger belonged to Jose P. G. Valdez, probably a butcher in St. Augustine, Florida. It includes his name and a list of clients on the front flyleaf and his name on the back flyleaf, as well a brief entry in Spanish on page 102. The ledger also lacks the first twenty-two pages, which presumably held his business entries. The remaining 185 pages are blank.
The back flyleaf includes computations to establish the ages of people in 1887 and 1889, probably students at the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania.
Indian art -- Pictorial works; Indian ledger drawings -- Pennsylvania -- Carlisle; Indian painting -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Material culture -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Pictorial works; Kiowa art -- Pennsylvania -- Carlisle; Kiowa Indians; Kiowa Indians -- Pictorial works; Kiowa painting -- Pennsylvania -- Carlisle; Peyote -- Pictorial works; Shields -- Pictorial works; Thunderbird (Legendary character) -- Pictorial works; Tipis -- Pictorial works; Ledger drawings; Doanmoe, Etahdleuh, 1856-1888; Koba, 1848-1880; Soule, William S. (William Stinson), 1836-1908; Stumbling Bear, Kiowa chief -- Pictorial works; Valdez, Jose P. G.; Wynkoop, Francis Murray, 1869- -- Autograph; Villagra Book Shop (Santa Fe, N.M.) -- Ownership
- Ledger, circa 1878-1880; (1 volume)
  - Copy drawing in graphite and colored pencil of the Thunderbird within an arc of lightning., circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 29)
    Scope and Contents
    Drawing attributed to Etahdleuh
    Copied from a muslin war cape painted by Black Chicken (also known as Siyo Sapa, Sayosapa, and Black Prairie Chicken), a Yanktonai Indian, circa 1870-1880, and formerly in the collection at the United States Indian School
  - Drawing in colored pencil of a beaded strike-a-lite bag and a painted parfleche, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 37)
    Drawing attributed to Koba
  - Drawing in graphite with watercolor of a beaded strike-a-lite bag between two diamond motifs., circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 39)
  - Watercolor of the head of an American Indian man in profile, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 45)
    Watercolor attributed to Koba
  - Watercolor self-portrait with a war shield riding a horse and chasing a buffalo, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 59)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Page 63, for a depiction of the same war shield
    See also: Page 87, for a depiction of the same war shield
  - Drawing in graphite and watercolor of a painted tipi, drying meat, a cooking pot suspended over a fire, and a war shield displayed on a tripod with an otter-wrapped crooked lance, together with a man and a wagon, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 63)
    See also: Page 59, for a depiction of the same war shield
  - Copy watercolor of a mystical, horned figure, circa 1878-1885 (Volume 1, Page 79)
    Painting attributed to Etahdleuh Doanmoe
    Copied from a rawhide drum painted by Black Chicken, circa 1870, formerly in the collection at the United States Indian School
  - Drawing in graphite with watercolor of six buttons of peyote (Lophophora williamsii), circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 81)
  - Drawing in colored pencil with watercolor of a painted tipi, and a war shield suspended on a tree behind the lodge, as well as a wagon, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 87)
  - Drawing in graphite with watercolor of geometric designs used in ceremonies of the Native American Church, including a shield, beaded blanket strip and a "half-moon" fireplace, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 91)
  - Drawing in graphite with watercolor of a Kiowa Indian shirt painted yellow with red fringe and a red, four-point star on the neck piece, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 99)
  - Drawing in graphite with watercolor of a yellow horse running and two bushes, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 105)
  - Watercolor of a buffalo bull, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 107)
  - Sketches in graphite of two horse heads and forelegs, as well as a sketch in graphite of the neck and mane of a horse, circa 1878-1885 (Volume 1, Page 109)
    Sketches attributed to Etahdleuh Doanmoe
  - Sketch in graphite that depicts the front elevation of a Greek Revivalist building, probably the mess hall at United States Indian School, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 111)
    Attibuted to an unidentified artist
  - Drawing in graphite with red and blue colored pencil showing the heads of two American Indian women, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 113)
    Attibuted to an unidentied artist
  - Drawing in graphite with watercolor of a yellow horse, circa 1878-1885 (Volume 1, Page 115)
    Drawing attributed to Etahdleuh Doanmoe
  - Drawings in graphite with watercolor of a beaded cradleboard, an American Indian in a school uniform, a dead tree, and a view of the Rainy Mountain in Oklahoma, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 117)
  - Drawings in graphite with watercolor of a stockade fort with reversed flag of the United States, a rifle, a knife and a war shield, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 121)
  - Drawing in graphite with watercolor of the forequarters of an elk stag and three bushes., circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 123)
  - Copy drawing in graphite of a studio portrait photograph that depicts Kiowa Indian chief Stumbling Bear (also known as Set-tim-geah) (1832-1903) created in 1869 by photographer William S. Soule (1836-1908), and a watercolor of a war shield with red-wool-cloth drape and eagle feathers, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 125)
    Drawing and watercolor attributed to Koba
  - Drawing in graphite of a leather belt decorated with brass upholstery tacks, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 127)
  - Drawing in graphite with watercolor of a beaded Kiowa Indian strike-a-lite bag, between two hour-glass motifs, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 129)
  - Drawings in graphite with watercolor by Koba that shows the forequarters of a horse, as well as a stylized figure of the inflamed, spotted body of a Kiowa Indian man, which a "smallpox year" in the tribal calendars., circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 133)
  - Sketch in graphite of a standing Kiowa Indian man wearing an eagle-feather headdress with buffalo horns, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 135)
    Sketch attributed to Koba
  - Drawing in graphite with watercolor of a train with an engineer operating a locomotive and railcars with American Indian passengers, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 145)
  - Watercolor of a dark-green Kiowa Indian war shield with two eagle feathers, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 171)
  - Watercolor of a Kiowa war shield with design of a charging buffalo, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 173)
  - Watercolor of a Kiowa war shield with abstract geometric design, circa 1878-1880 (Volume 1, Page 175)